[Music]
what's up folks this is addy ads and
this is public intelligence we have an
awesome guest this afternoon we have
john kiriakou cia torture whistleblower
former intelligence officer for the
central intelligence agency and now a
best-selling author
and speaker
and he's also a uh a writer as well and
we're going to talk about the outlets he
he has written for
his awards as well he won the 2016 sam
adam award for i think his courage in
whistleblowing
and he
also spent two years at loretto which is
a a federal prison in pennsylvania so
we're going to talk about that as well
but i want to thank you for coming on
the show john and i just tell you again
it was a pleasure to meet you in person
in d.c thank you pleasure is mine happy
to be here
of course uh and i wanted to ask you how
you thought the conference went uh it
was a couple weeks ago now but you had i
think the best speech there oh thank you
yeah i think that seemed to be the
consensus but yeah how did you think it
went i i loved the conference you know
it's
it's an unusual kind of conference
because
most of these things the the washington
institute the middle east institute
uh they have a very strong
pro-israel bias to them
and
and this one
doesn't this one is
far more pro-palestinian
and talked about issues that
you really don't talk about at these
other issues at these other conferences
and and the
the cast of
of speakers and even the guests you know
there were some remarkable guests
at this thing
it just made
it just made it such a
a worthwhile way to spend a couple of
days and then getting to meet
you know roger waters was
thrilling
yeah yeah definitely i agree sir it was
it was great to meet both you guys and
you know getting
to meet new authors and new material
uh new uh online outlets uh as well but
i wanted to ask if we could take it back
a little bit yeah i learned you were
actually a teacher at one point in time
in my research for this interview i
wanted to ask you how long you taught
for and why you why you decided to start
and stop teaching and then what it is
you taught
sure
my mom and dad were both public school
teachers
uh
my dad for he was mostly a principal but
for 44 years
uh and and about um
38 of those years were as a principal my
mom was a an elementary school teacher
for 20 years
and when i was in grad school
i was going to school full-time
and
having a part-time job just wasn't
enough to to pay the expenses so
i got a job teaching american history
and
an american government
at a
a small private school on dupont circle
here in washington
that was called the emerson preparatory
institute and at the time this was in
the late 1980s it was it was primarily
for recovering alcoholics and drug
addicts
and so it was very
like
specifically tailored to people who also
had to you know think about scheduling
treatment and therapy and stuff like
that
so i only did it for two years because
um like i say i was in grad school at
the time
and um
and it was two years well spent it was a
great experience it really was
and you taught was it history
uh-huh american history and american
government
okay and if you didn't make the decision
to go into the cia would it uh you know
what is another career path you think
you might have taken
honestly i really really wanted to go to
uh to film school i wanted to make uh
documentaries yeah i wanted to make
documentaries and i know that there's no
money in documentaries there never is
but um
but it always fascinated me and it's
funny now i've been in
man i'm not exaggerating 25 30
documentaries one of them was nominated
for an emmy um one was nominated for an
oscar
it's uh it's worked out kind of nicely
yeah so in in a sense you you achieve
that goal uh anyways although you are
kind of you're in front of the camera
behind it right behind it yeah
and but i wanted telling stories in that
respect and a good documentary can
really tell a good story
do you have some favorites uh that you
can share with us or documentaries that
have uh really influenced you
one that i saw recently that
was just incredible was um searching for
sugar man have you ever heard of that
one
i haven't no it was it was nominated for
an academy award back in i think 2016
and it was about this uh this folk
singer who um
came out with an album that nobody
really listened to although he was
really good
and um
and then came out with a second album
that even fewer people listened to
and then he just sort of disappeared but
what he didn't know
was that someone had smuggled these
albums into apartheid era south africa
and he ended up selling more albums in
south africa than the beatles and elvis
and uh and nobody ever told him
one of the record label executives just
stole the money
and so
nobody knew was he still alive
uh
where did he live and the documentary
filmmakers decided to try to find him
and they found him in detroit he's a
plumber
and um lives in this ramshackled falling
down house
uh but he ended up
going to south africa when they told him
that he was the most popular
folk singer in the country he ended up
selling out 20 dates
and uh has gone back a couple of times
it was a it was a wonderful
story of you know the little guy
finally winning
yeah yeah sure wow that's great i might
have to check that one out and that came
out in 2016 you said so probably it's
still on i saw it on amazon not too long
ago really terrific
okay okay excellent uh and as far as the
the cia goes what do you think is uh not
even just one thing but what are
what's an understanding at least a basic
understanding that the layman should
have about the cia and and how it works
because i think a lot of people don't
they don't even know the difference
between the cia and the fbi for example
yeah yeah a lot of people don't know the
difference between the ci and the fbi
um
you know the in the easiest terms
the cia's job is very very simple it's
to recruit spies to steal secrets period
that's all they're supposed to do and
then on the analytic side of course
the analysts
evaluate those secrets to provide the
policy maker with the best informed
uh background to allow the policy maker
to actually make the policy
uh that's not really the way things have
turned out
the cia does a lot of things that
are
illegal
or unethical or inappropriate
um they do that because there's no legal
pushback
they do it because the oversight
committees in the house and senate don't
stop them
and um and so they've ended up
sort of encroaching on
on the
fbi's mission
not to say that the fbi hasn't done
exactly the same thing
you know
and uh and has encroached on the cia's
mission
but either way it's it's wrong it's
likely unconstitutional
and it should be reigned in and it
hasn't been i think at the most basic
level that's something americans should
understand it is illegal
for the cia or nsa for that matter to
collect information on american citizens
yet they do it every single day
and that's just wrong
and what are your
thoughts on
the other famous whistleblowers because
you're you are among the most famous and
the first uh official cia agent to to
confirm
torture on record
as we know
uh do you have relationships with them
uh do you read their books uh did you
guys know each other before uh yeah what
is that like yes yes and yes
um you know it's funny
we have like a little
club
you know for lack of a better word
um
we're all in touch we get together for
dinner we hang out at conferences
we call each other
we read each other's books we're in each
other's books
um and i i couldn't have gotten through
my own experience without the support of
these guys
the the most important for me have been
tom drake from nsa uh jessalyn radak
from the justice department and daniel
ellsberg of the pentagon papers fame
they've become just wonderful very close
friends
to a very slightly lesser
extent uh
bill binney from nsa and kirk wiebe
um
daniel hale the drone whistleblower
lisa ling another drone whistleblower
even ed snowden you know um
ed's dad came to visit me in prison
uh because i had written this i had
written an open letter to ed snowden
that somehow went viral
millions and millions of hits it was it
was carried everywhere and then i
followed it up with a private letter um
that i was able to get to him through a
mutual friend at the cia
and um and his dad came to prison to
thank me for it ed's a little tougher to
stay in touch with just because of his
own circumstances
um and he's trying very hard to keep a
very low profile right now because of
the war in ukraine and all but um
but you know all of us stood up for each
other and uh
and looked out for each other and if i
didn't have the support of
of the likes of tom and jessalyn and and
dan ellsberg i i'm not sure what i would
have done
and
did you reach out to them or did they
reach out to you no no they they all
reached out to me
wow wow you know when i first met
jessalyn radak it was at her law offices
it was about four days after i had blown
the whistle
and um
and uh she
had been quoted in the washington post
talking about my case
and so a mutual friend put us in touch
and i went to her law office to steer
and i was there for i don't know it was
a long time it was like two and a half
hours three hours
and at the end of it i said to her
listen i want to thank you for taking
the time to speak to me because i know
that you only
handle whistleblower cases and i'm not a
whistleblower
and she said but you are a whistleblower
and i said no i'm not i i'm just
i'm just a guy who you know said
something
and she said there's a legal definition
of whistleblowing it's bringing to light
any evidence of waste fraud abuse
illegality or threats to the public
health or public safety you're the
poster boy for whistleblowers
and it opened my eyes just her saying
that opened my eyes and
the next thing i i knew
you know people were arranging
these discrete dinners i went to dinner
once at
at a
uh publisher's house she was a big time
supporter of whistleblowers and and tom
drake was there and
um
daniel ho who you know
single-handedly brought down don't ask
don't tell by chaining himself to the
white house fence
and daniel ellsberg and um
wow a whole bunch of people
and the fbi followed
all of us to the dinner like
independently of one another like i've
got surveillance tom has surveillance
dan has surveillance and they all follow
us to this one house where we're all
getting together for dinner so we
ordered them a pizza
and we had it delivered just to show
them you know you guys aren't
so discreet as you think you are we all
spotted you
right right yeah and then at the dinner
they followed all of us home
wow wow and and that was something too
that went on for for years that the
surveillance did
you and then towards the end it was just
it wasn't even surveillance it seemed it
was just like intimidation right like
yeah yeah yeah yeah and that was some
five years right
five years it went on yeah it started in
early 2000 uh
well actually
it was five years that i knew about it
it had actually started three years
before
so we're talking about eight years of
surveillance
msp so much money of the
imagine yeah so much money
you know i actually
i filed a freedom of information act
request asking how much money was spent
on my investigation and prosecution and
they refused to answer it
oh wow yeah my lawyers
estimated like six to ten million
dollars
like was it really worth it
you know
yeah society better off having spent 10
million dollars to follow me to target
or outback steakhouse you know or church
that one made me mad i was like wow
that's these people have no shame at all
and then and sat in the
sat in the uh the pew directly behind me
like what do they think i'm gonna do in
the middle of church at least sit in the
balcony yes exactly
exactly
could you share with us john uh
if you can't that's fine but general
tips how does if somebody tells you're
under surveillance uh is there anybody
any way to tell that you can share with
us any tips
you know i i have a book that's coming
out next month called the cia insider's
guide to surveillance and surveillance
detection oh wow that's awesome so yeah
there there are
several things that you could do first
of all the the first rule of
surveillance is don't let them know that
you know
that they're following you right don't
try to lose them don't go the wrong way
down the one-way street don't speed up
and slow down and speed up and slow down
just go about your normal business
and the reason that you do that is
because
they're looking to see if they can
detect an anomaly if you're doing
something that just simply doesn't make
sense
like for example
if you're going to do a surveillance
detection route to see if you're being
followed
it's going to go in four phases
the first phase is just leaving from
your
home or place of work
and going to your first cover stop
now your first cover stop should be a
totally normal
thing that you would do in your
neighborhood like 7-eleven
right you wouldn't drive 10 miles across
town to go to a 7-eleven over there that
doesn't make any sense
but you would stop at a 7-eleven in your
neighborhood
so you pull in you get out you buy a
diet coke you get in the car
and then
you get off the main roads and start
using what are called black roads
black roads are like little neighborhood
cut throughs not highways not major
roads
that way you can see who's going to
follow you into that neighborhood
and then you do that using black roads
to your second cover stop stop
now the second cover stop maybe
you're taking your clothes to the dry
cleaners
or you stop at a wine shop or you stop
at home depot and buy a light bulb or
something right
and then you can see if people go inside
the establishment with you
to see if you're you know to see what
you're doing in there
then the third phase is called the
aggressive phase you you make use of
this technique called uh stair stepping
where you go one block make a right one
block make a left one block make a right
one block make a left like a stair step
okay
and you can see
who's making these turns with you
also you're you're keeping in mind
you know i saw that blue pickup truck an
hour ago
on the other side of town
or i remember that minivan because it
had this bumper sticker on it so
think to yourself have i seen these
places or have i seen these these
vehicles rather before
the the definition of surveillance is
multiple sightings at time and distance
where you see the same vehicles or the
same people at different places
at different times during the course of
the day
then the fourth um
phase
to your final destination is called the
provocative phase
this is where you're driving and it
doesn't make any sense you're you're
pulling into people's driveways to make
a u-turn or you make an illegal u-turn
or you go around the block like all the
way around the block and end up where
you started that's just to shake
somebody loose if you've missed someone
earlier in the in the route you can
shake them loose and see
um you know finally definitively if
you're being followed but normally i
would say just go about your normal
business
you know your neighborhood better than
they do so it would make sense for you
to take these black roads and cut
throughs and shortcuts through
neighborhoods but just don't do
something that just simply doesn't make
sense because it's going to be alerting
to them you want them to to conclude
that what you've been doing while
they've been following you
is totally normal behavior
so you're not interesting to them and
they're going to drop off and they're
going to follow somebody else
but if you like i say you drive 10 miles
across town to go to a 7-11 and buy a
diet pepsi and then drive all the way
back home
yeah that's not normal nobody does that
right right wow and when again does that
uh book come out
uh
they just delayed it believe it or not
because of the supply chain disruption
there's no paper to print the books on
so it's it's going to be may 25th now
that's pretty rare for a writer with a
book deal to get a delay isn't it
yeah and they've delayed it three times
now it was oh wow february
wow there's no paper
that's amazing that's amazing yeah that
was like one of the first things i saw
shooting up in terms of inflation was
the you know the the wood paper lumber
uh and that's much but as a writer that
must be
kind of nice to get that extension it's
a little
well
yeah because i i also have to send
everything i write to the cia's
publications review board
and they have to clear it and make sure
i'm not saying anything classified
i found it interesting that you you said
that they don't care what you say on air
but just as long as you don't write it
is that correct
yeah usually um because
their argument is if you say something
on the air it could have been edited to
make it sound like it was something
different from what you said
so you're kind of covered for that i do
know a couple of guys a couple of former
cia officers who if they know they're
going on the air will write something
out and submit it for clearance and then
stick to their talking points that makes
for a terrible interview it makes for a
very boring and very stilted
interview but if you write something
you have to send it to the publication's
review board for clearance for the rest
of your life
wow wow yeah and likewise you have a
it's like a lifetime secrecy class too
yeah even though they they came they
came after you with everything and but
the kids yeah and and the frustrating
thing is you know you look at people who
who did far worse than i did i was
prosecuted for confirming the last name
of a former cia colleague to a reporter
who never made the name public never
and then you've got david petraeus
who confirmed the names of 10 covert
operatives
to his adulterous girlfriend
and
got 18 months of unsupervised probation
or
i won't say his name because he's never
been charged with a crime there was a
disgruntled former cia officer
in bethesda maryland
who
made a website
and named
named 17 cia officers who had wronged
him during the course of his career half
of them were undercover and he was never
charged with a crime never
and i said to my lawyer at the time this
was in 2012.
how how do they let him get away with
something like that they come down on me
like a ton of bricks
and they let him just have this website
where he's outing people my lawyer said
because he didn't blow the whistle on
the cia's torture program
that's what this is about and
that was true
i i thought it was kind of tragic how
you said the initial i think it was you
said 12 or 13 guys in the room that you
were with there was actually one other
guy who said no at first yes and then he
and then he turned he turned into the
dark side
yeah i thought that was really sad it
was like a really small anecdote but i
was like oh so you weren't completely
alone for a little bit
for a little bit
how did you you know and you know maybe
you want to talk about uh cool you do
write about it in your book you
mentioned your your wife's uh you know
support really was perhaps the biggest
uh thing that got you through uh and you
mentioned the the whistleblowers as well
uh but your own cia training and
experience but regardless as well
prepared as you were
i'd have to imagine that was a really
like stressful uh experience those first
you know few weeks yeah
um you know at my sentencing uh my
lawyers asked the judge to send me to a
minimum security work camp
and at a minimum security camp they're
they're across the street from maine
prisons at a minimum security camp there
are no
fences the doors are unlocked there are
no bars on the windows you're free to
come and go as you please
so long as you're you know you're sort
of on your honor not to abscond
you uh
probably will end up working in town you
know there was a university in town
people were janitors there
um
so
my attorneys asked her to send me to
this work camp and the prosecutors had
no objection
so she says okay
i order that
you serve your sentence at the minimum
security work camp at loreto
pennsylvania and what you do
as odd as it might sound when you when
you surrender to start a prison sentence
you just drive up to the prison and
knock on the door
and say hi i'm john kiriakou i'm here to
turn myself in
so i did that and they said oh you got
to go across the street to the main
prison first and then they'll process
you there and then they bring you back
over here i said okay
so um
so i went across the street knocked on
the door i'm john kiriakou here to turn
myself in
and um
and they they you know put you through a
metal detector and they x-ray your
jacket and whatever
and then the cop starts to lead me
around to the back of the actual prison
and i said no no
i'm supposed to be at the camp across
the street
and he he chuckled and he said not
according to my paperwork you're not
and i told myself take it easy there's
nothing you can do
if you raise a
ruckus
they're going to put you in solitary so
i didn't say a word
it took them about
40 minutes to process me
you know they they take your picture
they put it on a little badge and you
have to wear this badge
and they gave me
you know
a prison uniform and
a towel and a roll of toilet paper and
sheets
so they take me to a bunk and the guy
says to me welcome home and he just
walks away
well
it took me
four days to get access to a phone
and i called my lawyers and i said hey
they put me in the actual prison with
the drug kingpins and the mafia dons i
said what do i do
and my lead attorney said oh man he said
we could file a motion but it'll be two
years before we get a hearing and you'll
be home by then he said i'm sorry buddy
you're gonna have to tough it out
so i thought well
i'm trained for this kind of thing
i've certainly lived in way worse places
around the world than loreto
pennsylvania
so
you know i thought i'm just gonna fall
back on my cia training and i'm gonna
make sure i stay at the top of the
social heap and keep myself safe i
actually wrote a book about it my second
book um and it won two literary awards
oddly enough um it's called climb like a
spy
my seat my um
how the cia taught me to survive and
thrive in prison and i have these 20
life lessons that the cia taught me
you know admit nothing deny everything
make counter accusations
uh
let others do your dirty work um
your mind can take more physical
punishment than your body thinks it can
stuff like that
so 20 these life lessons and i use
examples for each one on how i was able
to
you know negotiate this
this maze in prison for for two years
i'm really loving reading your your book
right now doing time like a spy thank
you yeah i'm i'm traveling right now so
i'm just doing it on the ebook but i'm
looking forward to get the paper back
and then your your new one as well
that's that's that's awesome at segwayed
my question perfectly well you know what
it's i have three of them coming out at
the on the same day so i have oh wow the
cia insider's guide to surveillance and
surveillance detection the cia insider's
guide to lying and lie detection
and the cia insider's guide to
disappearing and living off the grid
hey i'll tell you something funny too
about that last one
yeah um i was on i was on this uh
podcast
like a right-wing extremist guy
but he's a nice guy right i i disagree
with him but i like him he's a nice guy
so he said oh would you come on my
podcast i said sure
so
we went to a commercial break and he
asked me so what are you working on and
i said oh i just finished these three
books and i told them
and the last one i said was the
insider's guide to uh disappearing and
living off the grid and he goes john
that book has right-wing extremism
written all over it
we have to do a
zoom lecture and
for a hundred dollars everybody gets a
copy of the book you'll make a fortune i
said hey that's a good idea so maybe
i'll try it
wow yeah that's a great idea uh yeah
yeah and if you want to talk a bit about
either of those because i think uh you
know a deception book is like lying book
right i think that that'd be really
interesting to to read about yeah
there's a lot out there i have a really
great relationship with um sky horse
publishing they've published my last
five books
and um
they they told me recently it was the
most fascinating thing that they found a
book
it was a manual a cia manual that was
published in 1955 on how to pick locks
and it's in the public domain because
it's so old
and so they just reissued it with a new
cover and much to their shock
it made number 10 on the new york times
best sellers list
wow so they asked me if i would um
if i would scour the internet find
whatever declassified cia manuals are
out there
and then maybe i could write a new
introduction for each one
and they can re-release them so i'm
looking at them right now i have one two
three four
i have five that i found on everything
from how to make a a
key mold out of mud if you're in the
woods
to um
let's see
the the field explosive guide the cia
writing style guide
uh how to recruit um spies to steal
secrets
there there are a lot of them
wow wow that's that's amazing the big
one is the cia torture guide called
kubar from the 1950s it's nasty
it's nasty and it takes lessons from you
know the the
communist chinese from the belgians and
the congo at the turn of the 20th
century from the vietnamese when they
were fighting the french it the nastiest
regimes in the world and it brings all
of their torture techniques into one
guide and that's what the cia was using
in the 50s and 60s
lord wow that's uh
yeah that's it's really really dark and
that's public domain the yeah public
domain it people call it kubar it's not
kubar it's k-u-b
b-a-r-r k-u
is a digraph that
it means a lot in the cia people
wouldn't understand it but k-u-bar is
the code is the code word
that was used for the early
torture program
okay and that was like you said mid 20th
century or yeah mid 20th century
yeah they published it in like 52 or 55
and then it came out again in the early
70s
okay okay wow and i would like to ask
you uh about your writing process so
what is that like uh how does that um
how does that manifest for you what do
you find works for you oh that's a
that's a great question you know it's
funny i i've given
hundreds upon hundreds of interviews and
nobody's ever asked me that before
um
i write a lot and in part it's because i
have trouble sleeping
and i figured
there's no sense in laying in bed
feeling sorry for myself when i can be
writing something and making four
hundred dollars you know
so uh
so i'll come down at two o'clock in the
morning i'll write 800 words i'll send
it to some you know newspaper and then i
go back to bed
uh when it comes to books
books are different i write in spurts
like for example
most of the books that i've written have
been commissioned
where the publisher will call me and say
hey i need sixty thousand words on xyz
and so i'll sit and it usually takes me
about nine months and i'll you know
write a book
there was one book my third book on abu
zubaydah where the publisher called and
said i need a book in 30 days and i
laughed i said it's not possible and he
said we really really need this book in
30 days
so they sent me a check and i i said to
my my wife um
i'm going to sit at the computer
every day and i am not going to get up
until i've written 2 000 words
and so i started the day after
thanksgiving and i finished the book the
day before christmas
but that's the fastest i ever wrote one
i'm writing one now
like for myself
honestly i think that in the end it's
going to be one of my most popular books
but i'm writing the definitive guide to
washington dc's historic cemeteries
it's something that i've always been
interested in there are some incredible
stories out there that are just
begging to be told
and uh honest to god the last couple of
weeks
there there were two days
this past sunday
and the week previous saturday where i
sat down and i wrote 10 000 words
each one of those two days
so
i'm going i'm writing this book so
quickly
that
i'm actually behind now on the
photography
you know i've i've got to take pictures
of all these
grave sites i've got to take pictures of
the cemetery entrances i have to look
through historic pictures of the people
who i'm writing about it's
i'm writing so fast that that i've just
gotten ahead of the rest of the book
do you
yeah go ahead john i gotta i wrote a i
wrote a 3 000 word piece for um
sheer post for robert shearer the other
day he's a former pulitzer prize-winning
journalist he's a professor now at usc
and he commissioned a 3 000 word piece
on the abu zubaida capture
so i wrote it and i sent it to him
i i'm very proud of the way i write i
require very little in the way of
editing
and um
i want to get there one day john
i'm just going to keep reading your
books i'm just going to keep reading
your books you know the best advice i
ever had i wrote the first draft of my
first book and i gave it to my wife
and asked her to read it and when she
finished it i said what do you think and
she said honestly i think it's terrible
and i said really
she said yeah she said it's so boring
and so dry it looks like a government
report
and i said i can't believe what i'm
hearing
and she said honey
i have listened to you tell these
stories a thousand times you should
write them exactly as you tell them
and it utterly changed my writing style
just that advice
so instead of writing in the way the cia
trained me to write
which really was like a boring
government report
you know to not have one extra word one
unnecessary word because the president
doesn't have time to to
focus on your extra words right
sure
so i completely changed my writing style
and
i started writing as if i were telling a
story
and so that that first book made number
five on the new york times bestsellers
list
doing time like a spy one forward
reviews memoir of the year and it won
the pen first amendment award one of the
big four with the pulitzer the pen
faulconer and the edgar allan poe
um i won that in 2016.
it was great advice
and so that's that's what i try to do i
try to be a storyteller so anyway i
wrote this three thousand word piece on
about the beta's capture
and i got a call this is about a week
ago i got a call from a guy and he said
you don't know me but i'm um i'm bernie
sanders uh literary agent
and i said oh how interesting i said i
love bernie sanders
and he said i just read your piece at
sheer post on abu zubaydah
would you be
interested in turning it into a book
and i said wow writing 3000 words on
torture is one thing but writing 60 000
words on torture is an entirely
different thing and he said i can sort
of guide you through the chapters you
know what i want you to address but he
said i think we can go back to random
house penguin saint martin's you know
one of the big ones
and i said yeah i said that sounds good
i think i'm gonna do
yeah wow fantastic congratulations john
i'm looking forward to that one as well
thank you and i wanted to to bring up
the the pen amendment award uh which
you you won uh and along with uh sibel
edmonds who i wanted to bring up because
of this this idea i had with my first
book of uh of public intelligence being
open source media combined with
whistleblowers yeah that kind of uh
distinguishes it from open source
intelligence was which doesn't mean
someone like yourself or miss edmonds so
i i kind of see that as the the solution
to the media problem uh that would be a
good one you know the soviets used to
call that mosaic intelligence oh
yeah that you can take open source
intelligence and information from
whistleblowers
put it together in a mosaic and even if
you don't have all the pieces of the
puzzle you can at least see what the
puzzle is
i love that i love that metaphor that's
great yeah yeah i think that's um so it
wasn't i just used a different term i
knew it wasn't a uh you know an original
idea i was like somebody else must have
thought of this yeah but i'm not sure
anybody's actually written about it i
think that would be very interesting
yeah yeah i'll send you my next edition
john for free uh
yeah of course sorry now i'll include
you in it uh as well uh and you know
other people that i've met along the way
because that's that's something too is
pretty much everyone in the book i've
either interviewed or had another
interaction with
but yeah what is your uh you know idea
for a solution to this because the media
is a huge problem i think the corporate
media certainly with getting people to
understand even basic things let alone
you know cia
skullduggery
yeah good question i think the bottom
line is that you have to be utterly
diligent in your own analysis of the
information
and i'll give you an easy and current
example
so
um a friend of mine
called me the other day she's
ethnic ukrainian but an american citizen
and she said
can you believe that we've killed seven
russian generals already it's incredible
it's going to turn the whole war around
and i said yeah i saw that i saw that
report but
what's the sourcing
what do you mean
i said we gotta look at the sourcing who
says we've that the ukrainians have
killed seven generals
well as it turns out the ukrainians say
it
so i mean who are these generals where
are their votes
right what are their commands
you can't just kill a general and then
the russians say oh well general's dead
well they're going to appoint somebody
else and they're going to make an
announcement
right or somebody in washington is going
to leak it
you can't just say
that you read this article and it said
that the ukrainians killed seven
generals so it's it's fact it's just
done it's fact
so
you know we've got to look at everything
with a very careful analytic eye one of
the things that i do as soon as i wake
up in the morning
you know as soon as i get out of the
shower i go straight to the computer and
i read everything from the far left to
the far right and everything in between
i read the new york times the washington
post the la times but then i go to
you know the huffington post and fox
news and
everything the drudge report you've got
to see what all sides are saying because
oftentimes they're saying things that
that are nothing like
what the others are saying
i tend to uh give a lot of weight to
things that come out of think tanks
but only after investigating to see
who's financing the think tanks
okay do you have any trusted think tanks
or or other outlets that you're like you
know i usually want to see what they're
saying and they're usually on the ball
it's easier to tell you which ones i
have a problem with sure sure i bet yeah
i have a problem with the center for
strategic and international studies at
georgetown university because they're
financed
by the biggest arms manufacturers and
defense contractors in america
so there's never ever any
criticism of u.s foreign policy or
defense policy never
and that's just not
acceptable on the left the brookings
institute is fantastic on the right
the american enterprise institute is
good but it's very very neocon
if you want more traditional
conservative it's the heritage
foundation but they tend to do more on
domestic policy than on foreign policy
um the the hoover institute is good on
foreign policy but it's also pretty
neocon
one of my go-to's is the reason
foundation and reason magazine they're
terrific
so
you know read read all of it
and um and then come to your own
conclusions
definitely and that's a that's a great
uh i think note to end on i want to be
respectful of your time john where can
people find your work uh where can they
support how can they do that thank you
very much well i um i write at
consortiumnews.com
at covertactionmagazine.com
at um
the sheer or sheerpost.com
and uh
i've got my own site at john
kiriakou.com and i'm on twitter and
facebook and all the usual places
excellent excellent thank you so much
john for joining me i hope you enjoyed
this again
and thank you to the audience for
joining us as well stay frosty folks and
we will see everybody next time